good afternoon
i'm very glad to be joined today and not
just by
patrick violence but by the chancellor
rishi sunak who is
going to tell us more in a moment about
our latest package to help this country
in its battle with kovid and i want to
thank rishi for
measures that will protect people's
livelihoods and protect
jobs and which will help us to deliver
our overwhelming
objective of getting the virus under
control
while keeping pupils in education and
keeping
the uk economy moving forward
i know that there are some people who
say this economic objective is so
important
that we should stop all measures to
control the virus
and stop restrictions of any kind on our
social lives
and on the way we run our businesses we
can't do that because
alas the maths is inescapable we would
face
many thousands more deaths and no
to answer one commonly posed question we
would not be able
to insulate the elderly and the
vulnerable
not in a society with so many
multi-generational
households no country has been able to
do that
and an uncontrolled expansion in the
number of
covid patients would mean that the nhs
would have
even less capacity to treat heart
patients and
cancer patients and to deal with all our
other medical needs so that's why
we reject that extreme laissez-faire
approach and then there are others who
say on the contrary that we need now to
lock the whole place down from jonah
groats to
land's end turn the lights out shut up
shop
close schools and universities and go
back to the same kind of lockdown we had
in march and april and may
and i have to say i don't believe that
is the right course
now not when the uh the psychological
cost of
locked down is well known to us the
economic cost
and not when it's being suggested that
we might have to perform
the same sort of brutal lockdowns again
and again in the months ahead and
not when there is such an obvious
variation
unlike last time between different parts
of the country so
that's why we're going for a balanced
approach
a middle course between the the cilla
of another national lockdown and the
charybdis of
an uncontrolled virus a regional
and local approach the same approach
that is now being followed
by some of the countries that are most
successful
in their fights against the virus and so
to all those who are enduring these
restrictions uh and who have been
enduring them
for so long uh in all parts of the
country
i want to repeat my thanks for your
bravery
uh for your patience and your public
spiritedness
and i i repeat there are clear signs
that our collective actions
are working yes they are the
reproduction rate of the virus is above
one
but thanks to the efforts of people
of all ages in following the guidance
and the rules
the r is about half its natural
rate and if we follow the guidance
together
and follow the rules then we can get it
done
and it's precisely because these
measures are burdensome
that from the beginning this government
has provided
unprecedented support to everyone in
this country
support worth 200 billion pounds to look
after jobs
and livelihoods and business
and as we adjust our campaign to fight
the virus
it's right that we should now produce a
new package
of support across the country in
addition
to the specific agreements we've reached
uh with lancashire
merseyside and others and
because it's far far better
to keep business going now rather than
to let those jobs go forever in a a new
national lockdown we will win this fight
against covid because we can see that
treatments are getting better and
medicines are getting better and testing
technologies
are getting better and we've shown
before
that we can drive the r down and
in the meantime we need to protect jobs
protect livelihoods
and put the uk in the strongest position
for an economic recovery i'm going to
hand over now
to the chancellor rishi suno thank you
prime minister good afternoon
our plan for jobs will support british
people
and businesses wherever they live and
whatever their situation
and just as we have throughout this
crisis we will listen
and respond to people's concerns as the
circumstances
evolve earlier today i announced three
new measures
first i'm making our job support scheme
more generous
for employers who can open safely but
who are struggling
with the impact of restrictions on their
business
instead of employees working at least a
third of their hours to qualify for
support
they will now have to work just one day
a week
and the government will significantly
increase the contribution it makes
towards people's wages with businesses
paying much less just five percent
toward the cost
of hours not worked this is one of the
most generous versions
of a short time work scheme in the world
it is better for business
better for jobs and better for the
economy
second we're doubling the value of the
self-employed income support grants
from 20 to 40 of average profits
meaning the maximum grant will increase
to 3750 pounds
and third we're introducing a new grant
scheme
for businesses in higher alert level
areas even if they can remain
open businesses in sectors like
hospitality leisure and accommodation
will be able to apply to their local
authority for cash grants
of up to two thousand one hundred pounds
per month
and these grants will be backdated to
august
this means we're being more generous to
businesses and places
which have been in higher alert levels
for longer
this is our plan a plan for jobs
for businesses for the regions for our
economy
for the country a plan to support the
british people
thank you thanks very much rishi uh
patrick can we get to you for the
today's slides please just uh
update you on some of the numbers so
this is a slide that i showed last week
the new numbers come out tomorrow but
it's a reminder that the
number of people in the uk thought to
have
uh kobe based on the office for national
statistics
survey last week was somewhere between
and 362 000 people over that period
we're expecting the new numbers tomorrow
and and this will be higher
i'm sure so that we continue to see an
increase in the total number of people
with the virus next slide please
that's one thing the prevalence the
number of people with the infection at
any one time the second is the incidence
the number of people
with a new infection every day
and again there are two numbers there
which are from last week which were the
estimates
again looking back from two big studies
the react study and the ons study
we get the updated ons data tomorrow but
the
modeling consensus suggests that between
53 and
90 000 new infections per day
may be occurring and obviously with that
number of infections
you expect to see an increase in
hospitalizations as well so the number
of infections
overall across the country continues to
increase
next slide please this shows the
hospital admissions the yellow bar
indicates from a month ago
and you can see an increase in the
number of patients admitted to hospital
every day with kovid which is up towards
a thousand
now and with the numbers of infections
you'd expect that to continue to
increase
and it's worth remembering that the
number of infections
leads to hospitalizations a week or two
later
and that in turn has the effect of
increasing intensive care unit
numbers and of course unfortunately a
number of people will die as a result of
that and that will increase a week or
two after that so we expect to see a
delay
from the number of infections through to
hospitalizations
through to the very serious consequences
and to death
next slide please a number of patients
in hospital with kovid
has increased again the yellow bar shows
from a month ago you can see the number
of patients across the uk
in hospital with covid and i just want
to make a point that the prime minister
has alluded to which is one of the
reasons that care for other conditions
like cardiovascular disease and oncology
cancer care gets affected is not the
measures taken to stop covid it's the
patients with codrid who start to occupy
bed so the more patients there are with
covid
the more the pressure on the healthcare
system overall and the more the
other conditions get affected because
people
don't have the capacity to deal with it
so it's very important to keep the
numbers of infections down
if we are to reduce the number of
hospitalizations
next slide please this is the r value
over time
from may through to now we're expecting
an
updated value for this tomorrow what you
can see
is r was very flat over the period of
the summer it was below 1
that means the epidemic is shrinking it
shrank over the period
up to august and then as measures were
released and people started to make more
contact
you can see that the r increased and
it's gone up to somewhere between
1.2 to 1.5 something like that
so it's about half of the natural r
which is around
three so it's definitely reflects
the huge effort that people have made to
try to
adhere to the various measures that are
in place the fact that we're wearing
masks we're keeping a distance we're
washing our hands we're doing the things
that we need to do
to try and reduce it has brought the r
down but this also means
that the epidemic is still growing as
long as r is above
one the epidemic continues to grow and
it will continue to grow
at a reasonable rate it's doubling
perhaps every 14 to 18 days
unless the r comes below one so that is
the a and i do want to just say
there are some areas where we begin to
see
real effects of what's happening so
there's some indications that amongst
young people
the rates are coming down or flattening
off a bit again
due to the huge efforts that people have
made to try to adhere to these
changes in behaviors that we need to
have in order to get this down
and in some areas of the country we can
begin to see a little bit of flattening
possibly
so the measures are having an effect but
we need to do
more if the aim is to get our below one
and to shrink
this epidemic i just want to show a
couple of slides now on
regional pictures next slide please this
is the
picture that we've shown before on the
left hand side the darker the purple the
higher the case numbers
what you can see is uh the entire
entirety of england is now purple so
that there are cases everywhere
increasing and some areas have got very
high numbers which if r stayed at one
those would stay at very high numbers on
the right hand side
is the speed with which growth is
occurring
so where it's brown the numbers are
increasing and the darker the brown the
greater the increase
so again in some areas this has slowed
down a bit
the rate of growth isn't as high as it
was in some areas
but overall this is growing continues to
grow
r is above one and therefore we should
expect to see
greater numbers next slide please
this is the regional breakdown in terms
of hospital admissions
and uh in keeping with the previous
slide what you can see is that the
northwest northeast yorkshire midlands
have the highest number of people in
hospital
again some possibility of of of um
beginning to see a decrease in the rate
of increase due to the measures that
people are taking
and you can see london is increasing but
at the lower level southeast east of
england and the south west of the lowest
but still
increasing so the regional picture is
different the country is essentially in
in different zones depending on the the
speed of
the increase and the overall numbers but
you can see there are increases across
the country as a whole
thanks very very much patrick let's go
to questions from the
from the public uh yvonne uh from
surrey first of all
uh the question i'd like to ask is in
the event of a
national or local lockdown where
specific businesses are ordered
to close what financial help will be
available
by the government to cover particularly
the cost of wages
to businesses who've not been
specifically told to close
but for whom there's no or limited
income because their clients or
customers
have been ordered to close and therefore
there's no work available
um well thanks very much yvonne i'm
going to uh ask rishi obviously to
to comment on on that as well but uh
we're doing everything we can to support
business throughout
this this crisis there are all sorts of
loans uh available grants available 25k
uh grants have been made available
there's uh cuts in
in vats is down to uh to five percent i
believe uh
business rates uh deferred uh doing all
sorts of things we can to
to support you and help you uh yvonne
but uh rishi
anything uh you'd like to say to
encourage you on
yes um so von there's a few things that
we've already put in place and a couple
more things that we announced today that
i think will be
of help to people in this situation if
you're
told specifically to close then your
business will be eligible the business
premises will be eligible for grants of
up to three thousand pounds
a month and that will last as long as
you have been told
to close and then for your staff the
wages of those staff will be paid by the
government at two-thirds
all the employer has to do is just
contribute to the national insurance
contributions
if they are owing a tour so i think
that's sensible and generous treatment
for people in those situations
for people who perhaps are suffering
from a supply chain as i think you're
talking about if you're involved in a
supply chain where businesses that you
supply are having a tough time
and that's having an impact on your
business i think a good example of that
is in tier two areas where some of the
restrictions
that we've got in place are having an
impact uh on businesses even though they
haven't been told to close but revenues
are down
uh whether that's hospitality or
otherwise we made two announcements
today that will help
businesses particularly in the
hospitality sector will be eligible
for grants worth 70 percent of the value
of the ones i mentioned earlier so that
will be up to 2
100 pounds per month a sum of that
amount will be made available to the
local authority for them to allocate at
their discretion
so it may be that they choose to do
something slightly different with it
but we will size the value of the grants
for the number of hospitality leisure
and accommodation businesses
in a particular tier 2 area and again
those grants will be available
monthly and then secondly for the wages
of
people of the staff and those types of
businesses the newly
generous job support scheme i think will
really help so you will be able to
rather than let go of those employees
they can work on reduced hours down to
now just
one day a week so they have some work
that they can do and for the rest of the
time
those employees will be paid two-thirds
of their normal wage
the employer just needs to pay five
percent of that the government
will pick up the rest of the bill so i
think that's again
as much support as we can provide to
help keep people
in work in businesses even though those
businesses are going through
a very tough time so hopefully as i said
those two things we announced today
coming on top of what we've already done
will make a real difference
thanks very much rishi and thanks yvonne
liam from
bradford asked what can and will you do
to encourage new and innovative business
to emerge at this time
a critical component of economic growth
which seems to have been
forgotten how can we share the risk um
well liam again i would say that
the uk is one of the most competitive
and dynamic uh environments to
uh to set up a business uh under any
circumstances
uh we have uh all sorts of advantages
but we now have
uh the advantages i said just now to
yvonne of
unprecedentedly low business rates
uh of vat we have a low corporation
tax uh and uh we we are
you know putting in fantastic
investments now in
a lot of the things that business will
need uh for uh for long-term growth the
investment in skills uh in
infrastructure in uh gigabit broadband
uh where we want to be leading the world
giving uh start-up businesses
uh the basic foundation on on which to
build
uh but uh rishi anything you'd like to
add to for liam yeah i think liam you're
absolutely right we're very lucky in
this country to have
fabulous entrepreneurial startup
companies uh they will help drive our
recovery so they haven't been forgotten
i'd probably point you to one particular
intervention we made earlier on in the
crisis and that was to create something
called the future fund
you heard the prime minister talk about
the various loan grants and guarantees
that we've made available throughout the
crisis
now they worked quite well for
traditional businesses which had cash
flows and profits before
you know they weren't well suited to
start-up businesses like the ones you're
describing
uh who were before that you know but
pre-revenue stage so what the future
fund did
is it shared the risk exactly as you
mentioned between the government
and investors and what we said is we
will match the
investment that private investors put
into these start-up companies whether
that's in a series
a round or a seed round or an angel
round
anywhere from a couple of hundred
thousand pounds all the way up to five
million
and that fund has proved to be really
successful i think it's been warmly
welcomed by the startup and
entrepreneurial
community all across the country and
it's funded
um just under a thousand companies uh so
far
and as you said i'm hopeful that that
will provide them with the financing
they need to survive through the crisis
share the risk with the taxpayer but
then emerge stronger on the other side
and help
drive our growth and recovery brilliant
thanks
uh let's go to laura kuhnsburg at the
bbc thank you very much prime minister
um firstly to you chancellor
um the problems with the first version
of your job scheme that you've rewritten
today
were obvious to many people in the
industry from the start
why do you keep underestimating the help
that people really
need and so patrick can i ask you if you
agree with scotland's chief medical
officer who's
told families there's no question of
anything like a normal christmas and
they should plan to celebrate
digitally and prime minister to you this
week
you've been to war with leaders in the
north of england you're still
leaving some workers on two-thirds of
their wages or telling them to claim
benefits
and cases of coronavirus keep on rising
this is really the kind of leadership
you think the country deserves
laura i think it's a perfectly fair
question to ask about the timing of this
i think if you think back to the summer
when we designed the job support scheme
in conjunction with business and
business groups and unions i think at
that point
we were looking forward to the economy
reopening and restrictions being lifted
now what we've seen in the last
especially last four or five
weeks as as these new restrictions have
been put in place
the impact they're having on the ground
has been highly significant particularly
to businesses
in the hospitality sector particularly
in these tier uh two areas
and it's the cumulative weight of all
these new restrictions has really if you
speak to anyone in this industry they're
seeing it in their numbers quite
um quite significantly over the past few
weeks and and that's why
you know as we've always said we will
adapt and evolve our response as the
situation changes now as the health
restrictions have changed and that's had
an impact on the economy i think it's
right
that we respond pragmatically and
flexibly to that because ultimately what
we're trying to do
is protect people's jobs and income and
the
measures that we've put in place today
i'm confident will do
just that and this will be now in place
for a while to come and i think it's
very generous and effective support
uh i think the numbers speak for
themselves they're increasing
and um they're not going to decrease
quickly and i think it's likely that
some
measures of restriction are going to
need to be in place for a while to try
and get
those numbers down obviously the quicker
you get the r below one
the quicker numbers come down and things
then give a bit of room
and so a lot depends on what happens now
over the next few weeks
at the moment the numbers are headed in
the wrong direction but as i say there
are some signs
in some places of a potential flattening
off of that and we need to wait and see
and monitor the numbers very very
carefully well
laura i must i'm afraid strongly reject
what you say about
me being at war with uh local leaders
that's that's not
not the case we've had great
conversations with
uh with uh local leaders mayors and
others in
uh liverpool in lancashire in in
yorkshire in the
in the in the west midlands south
yorkshire i should say
uh london and uh everybody has come to
the table
shown leadership stepped up to the plate
and
agreed to help bring the r down in that
particular area which is what we
we need to see i'm grateful also to andy
burnham uh
in uh greater manchester where uh where
he's agreed to help uh bring the yard
down with a package of measures in
in tier three and as as patrick has has
just said
thanks to the efforts of uh people
across the country
we are starting uh to see uh some
progress and it is early days yet and it
will be
tough but i really think that uh people
do
think across the country that this
balanced approach
avoiding another full-scale national
lock down and avoiding letting the virus
rip is the
is the right way forward and that is
what we are
uh pursuing uh balanced middle course
relying on uh local cooperation and
laura
i must you know as i say i disagree
we've had uh fantastic and extensive
uh local cooperation and yes it's tough
but we will certainly get through it
very well let's go to beth rigby of sky
news
thank you prime minister is the back
dated tier 2 business support today and
acknowledgement that you were not
supporting parts of the north of england
properly for weeks during the summer
andy barnum's right isn't he when he
says that you have
neglected the north and isn't this
announcement today
an attempt to right that wrong and sir
patrick
at a sage meeting on may the first uh
the sage committee agreed
that at least 80 percent of contacts
would be needed in the test and trace
system
to make it effective the test and trace
scheme
is contacting less than 60 percent now
how disappointing is that and what are
the implications of it
in terms of tackling this disease
um beth no the the the issue uh
is really one of of basic
of fairness is between uh various parts
of the country that are
having to experience regional uh
restrictions that's what we were trying
to achieve in the
uh in the last 10 days what we're doing
what we're doing now
is is bringing forward measures that are
designed to help businesses that have uh
you can't trade as they normally uh
would uh and are experiencing you know
a fallen income as as rishi has said
that's what we're trying to do we're
doing it and we're doing it across the
whole
country and it and it's it's backdated
uh as you know
uh to to august but uh rishi
i think i just echo what you said prime
minister beth
this is simply about fairness it's about
treating people the same
wherever they live and whatever their
situation all the interventions that
we've put in place
are there on a national basis and as
different parts of the country
experience
different restrictions at different
times our various
support measures whether it's grants for
businesses or the job support scheme
will be there to help them
their businesses support their wages at
whatever time that is but we approach
everything
uh from a position of wanting people to
have the equal support wherever they are
not just within england but in every
part of the united kingdom as well
thanks very much beth let's go to ben
kentish of lbc
oh sorry patrick yes um so on the on the
uh test and trace um it it's
undoubtedly the case that test trace and
isolation becomes much more difficult to
have an
impact once numbers are high so it's
much more effective when numbers are low
that's the first point
the second point is that i think the
testing system has ramped up the numbers
they're able to do quite effectively
but it's really important to concentrate
on numbers of
contacts isolation as quickly as you can
and getting things back as quickly as
you can ideally to get the whole process
done within 48 hours
and it's very clear there's room for
improvement on all of that and therefore
that will be diminishing the
effectiveness of this but the
effectiveness anyway
of test and trace is less when numbers
are high than it is when numbers are low
thanks very much as ben kentish of lbc
then you need to unmute or somebody
needs to unmute you
can you hear me now yes gotcha thank you
prime minister i wanted to follow up on
that issue actually because countries
like
south korea germany and taiwan have
shown that there is an alternative
to the sort of restrictions that much of
the uk is now under and that is a
functioning test and trace system
uh we're testing more people than ever
but clearly something's going wrong for
example
in june prime minister you said you
wanted a hundred percent of test results
to be back
within 24 hours today the current figure
is just 15
so what do you think's gone wrong there
and when can you assure the british
public
that that system will be effective
enough to start to control the virus
as it has in other countries and just
very quickly for the chancellor
unprecedented times wherein clearly
unprecedented spending
is needed to support people but with uk
debt hitting 2 trillion
the highest since the 1960s how long do
you believe that can go on for and how
concerned are you
about that figure well uh first of all
ben on your on your point about about
nhs test and
trace uh look i you know i share
people's frustrations and i understand
uh totally why we do need to see faster
turnaround
times and uh uh we do need to
uh do need to improve it we need to we
need to make sure that people who
do get a positive uh test uh self
isolate that's that's the
absolutely crucial if this thing is is
going to work in the way that it
that it can but i i just would stress to
you ben that the the achievements of the
testing operation have been
uh colossal you know they have moved
from uh a capacity of
of i think three thousand uh two
thousand tests
per day uh to about 300 000 now we were
we've tested uh 26 we've done 26 million
tests more than any other
uh country uh in in europe and they are
on track to reach
a capacity of 500 000 by
the end of this month um and and the
technology
is improving the whole time but the
crucial thing
to get nhs test and trace to work is
that if you
test positive then you've got to
to self-isolate and don't forget that
there's a
uh you know 500 pounds to help you with
the cost of that
but also a 10 000 pound fine for for not
doing so the thing depends
on people self-isolating and breaking uh
the
the transmission it is helping a bit
already to
to break uh the transmission about a
million people uh
as i say have been have been a million
contacts have been
have been reached but uh there is more
that it can do
if everybody complies once they're
contacted uh by nhs tests and trace
ben you're right to highlight the
unprecedented increase in borrowing
that's happening this year and the
consequent rise in our debt levels to
close to 100
of debt to gdp and as you said those are
unprecedented numbers at unprecedented
times
now whilst it is right to act i think
with scale
during a crisis like this to try and
protect jobs and employment and
ultimately
that will protect our economy in the
long run it's also right that because of
those numbers that you highlighted that
we always have one eye
on the long-term public finances because
we want to make sure that we are careful
with that
it's clearly not sustainable to carry on
acting in this way
forever so as we continue intervening in
the economy
it's right that that is targeted and
effective
and done in a way that we won't always
be able to do absolutely everything that
everyone would like us to do and it's
because of that
that uh because of the things that you
highlighted that will be the case that
we've got to have one eye
on the long-term health of the economy
and public finances
and make sure that you know once we get
through this we can return those public
finances and the economy to a strong and
sustainable position
uh thanks very much rishi let's go to
chris smith of the times
uh thank you chancellor firstly just
picking up on your
last point given that the government
strategy now is to suppress the virus
until a vaccine was found and
having accepted the need for more
support today and saying it will be in
place for a while to come can you
guarantee that this level of help
will continue to be available until a
vaccine is in widespread
use and then to prime minister and
patrick on test and trace against
patrick you said that it's more
effective when numbers are low and it's
diminishing effectiveness as cases rise
so have we now
missed our moment effectively for this
system to work is it salvageable our
case is now just
increasing too quickly to keep up
chris i mean i'll let the promise from
patrick comment on the vaccine and the
part that that plays or doesn't in the
medium term strategy but what we wanted
to do was give
businesses and employees some certainty
and ability to plan
through you know what is clearly going
to be a difficult winter period
so what we have said is that the job
support scheme which starts on november
1st
when furlough finishes will last for at
least six months so it will last through
to the spring uh there will be a review
point in the middle so we can have a
look at it and make sure that it's
working well
um but that that support in that in its
guys will be there
through this difficult period through to
the spring to give people that certainty
and because we know as a prime minister
said a while back this is something that
will be a fact of our lives
um for some months to come i think more
broadly
most of the economic interventions we've
made also now have that predictability
through to the spring whether it's the
business rates
holidays or the changes we've made some
of the loan programs or the vat cut for
hospitality
again all of that will provide cash
support to businesses and people
you know throughout this period but i'll
let the prime minister patrick talk
about
the kind of medium-term outlook well i
just add uh
one obvious point um chris
to what rishi has just said and that's
you know clearly this is
what we're announcing today is billions
more going into
to support the uh the uk economy support
jobs
and and livelihoods and that's right
it's far better to
to do that and keep uh the economy going
because we're going to have to pay this
money back
and we want to be in a position where
the uk economy where you know companies
are kept alive jobs uh supported uh
people's skills
are maintained their energies are
maintained
so that the uk can bounce back as
strongly as possible
uh once as you say uh we we get the
virus uh
back under control um and that's and
that's the
objective and uh you know i think that
if you look at the
uh the way the science is changing and
you look at the
uh the improvements in
uh in uh treatments in therapies uh in
drugs
um look at the changes we're seeing in
and the improvements in
uh in you know some some changes in in
the mortality rates
i i am confident that we will get
through this very well
in due course but for the moment uh and
improvements in testing technologies
uh as i said uh last week really
interesting improvements in testing
technologies
but for the moment we have to use uh the
same
tools that uh we've got which is uh the
social distancing
measures the uh all those all those uh
restrictions that
we put in place and we have to do that
at a local and a regional
level because that's the commonsensical
thing to do
and if we do it together in the way that
we can
and we follow the guidance together in
the disciplined way that we can and
by the way the way that people of all
age groups seem to be doing
across the country then you know we will
drive that r
down again and we will get it under
control and in the meantime
we would have supported our businesses
kept them alive
kept jobs uh going and we'll be in a
better position
to come out of it that's that's what
we're doing uh patrick
on vaccines i think you know things are
progressing well there are vaccines that
produce an immune response they're in
phase three clinical trials we should be
seeing some data readouts over the
course of this year
but i remain of the view that the
possibility of sort of wider spread use
of vaccines isn't going to be until
spring or so next
next year by the time we get enough
doses and enough
understanding of the outputs to to use
them now we may get a few doses this
side of christmas
maybe something could happen but i think
we should more realistically be looking
at spring and of course there are no
guarantees until
the studies have read out so we need to
be cautious and carry on
but there is a good progress in terms of
the vaccines
in terms of testing trace the number of
cases
test and trace will work effectively
across parts of the uk where
cases are lower that's when it can work
most effectively it has much less of an
impact
at the areas where you've got very high
levels and that's why additional
measures are taken and that's why
additional
isolation measures having to take
difficult decisions around
premises that need to be shut and so on
that's why they need to be taken
because at that point you can't really
control it
any other way than by stopping contacts
and
stopping contacts in environments in
which transmission is most likely to
take place
and then what test and trace does above
that and isolate is to try and remove
from circulation as far as you can those
people who are infectious
and as new testing methods come on on
train that may be more possible
more widely but at the moment it's very
difficult to remove
everybody who's infectious from a
situation where you've got high levels
which is why it's so important to get
them down
and why it's so important to to
self-isolate if you
if you get a positive test because that
if that doesn't happen then
obviously tests that a lot of the force
of test and trace
uh is is lost uh let's go to richard
partington of the guardian
thank you very much um question for for
you prime minister and the chancellor
um i wanted to ask why the government
was prepared to go to the wall
earlier this week over five million
pounds with andy burnham
when you were preparing to announce
billions of pounds
of more support today through this
expansion in the job support scheme
the chancellor and the community
secretary were pictured meeting
business leaders in london this morning
and does this mean that london is of a
higher priority
than the north of england for the
government
and then a second if i may why wait so
long
to announce these major reversals in
policy
when business leaders will have been
making decisions about what to do when
the furlough
scheme ends for several months now uh
does this not have a detrimental effect
on employment
and should the government not have acted
quicker
i mean sorry uh richard i i think you
directed the question of both of us but
i'll
i'll i'll quickly say my my my bit look
this was the the negotiations between uh
regional
uh leaders between metro mayors was all
about fairness that's what that
uh discussion was about it was about
making sure everybody got the same
package what we're trying to do now
is address a uh a national issue which
is that
uh obviously since the virus started to
come up again uh
there's been much more concern uh
particularly in amongst the business
uh community about the people's ability
to protect uh jobs and livelihoods
uh because of the effects of the of the
virus and as the
as the campaign adjusts the fight
against the virus
changes and obviously uh we change our
response that's that's only
that's only logical but but rishi yes i
echo that prime minister i think where
we richard when we designed the job
support scheme together with businesses
that you mentioned about and unions it
was done
over the summer with a view to the
economy being open restrictions being
lifted now obviously the last few weeks
that has not been as we as those
businesses had expected those
restrictions were coming back they were
having a cumulative effect on the ground
particularly in tier two areas
particularly
in hospitality and that's been the
cumulative weight of the changes
and the impact more broadly on consumer
confidence that we've seen
and that's why we've been in discussions
to try and see what changes we could
make that would do what we want to do
which is to try and protect jobs
and employment at this difficult time
and regard to the the meeting this
morning you're right we i was meeting uh
together with the community secretary
with representatives from businesses
unions
and indeed um in particular the
hospitality sector
there were plenty of people on on zoom
as well indeed from
i remember from merseyside and north
yorkshire as well as other places around
the country so i wouldn't take
anything from the fact that the meeting
would happen to be held in london and
you're right that was held
in a restaurant that was close to the
public at the time and was used as a
meeting for us for franco mancha
and i think it's important that we
highlight the particular impact of
what's happening on the hospitality
sector and that's why we were there
to bring that issue to light that's what
we were discussing
how are these social restrictions having
an impact on hospitality businesses
like that across the country and how can
we adapt and evolve our support
to try and help those businesses protect
as many jobs as people there are two
million people who work in that sector
i've said repeatedly that those people
typically are younger
women ethnic minorities on lower pay and
it is a matter of social justice that we
do what we can to try and protect as
many of those jobs
as possible thanks very much let's go
lastly to jane kirby of the press
association
jane you need to unmute unmute jane here
we go
sorry um so patrick just picking up on
what you were saying about vaccines
if we get a decent level of rollout by
next spring
how soon after that can people expect to
stop having to social distance and wear
mass
or do you think that those measures are
going to be in place for much of the
rest of 2021
and prime minister if circuit breakers
in wales and northern ireland are shown
to be more effective
than three-tier um restrictions
uh which some of your own advisers have
said are useless
will you change your mind
well i'm not going to speculate on how
effective the vaccines are going to be
we will see the readout from the
clinical trials over
the next months we'll see some i hope
within the next
couple of months we should start seeing
outcomes once we know how effective
the vaccines are then and how
applicable they are to different groups
then you can start working out
how to use them best but you can't do
that until you've seen the results of
safety and efficacy
and when you see that you can then start
to judge what impact that's going to
have but clearly the aim of vaccination
is to try to take most of the load of
of the infection spread onto the vaccine
in order to be able to release other
measures and that's got to be
an aim that we would all wish for and
that's why
so many companies around the world are
working on vaccines and why there's been
such remarkable progress and
it is remarkable if you look at um
history up till now
vaccines have never been made in
anything like this time frame it's been
at least five years and so to be where
we are now is remarkable
uh thanks very much well i mean i really
hope that we do make
uh progress with uh vaccines like you
know i i
won wonderful that patrick is uh is is
so optimistic if i can put it out that
way
uh about them um you know i but we can't
jen in my view rely on that we've got to
keep going uh
it may happen uh we're working flat out
to ensure that it does
uh but we we can't just count on that uh
and that's why we have to
do all the other things that that we're
doing and
um you know you ask the the the same
question everybody really
is asking should we just go back into
another national
lockdown and then uh you know possibly
have
an another one after that and another
one
after that and i think that that really
would be economically
uh socially uh psychologically really
very damaging and difficult for
for the country we all remember what it
was like in uh in march
and april uh there were lots of costs
particularly costs to uh
kids who are kept out of school uh
there's a big social
injustice uh there's a big there's
damage to people's
uh mental health uh it's it's to say
nothing of the economic
uh consequences of that kind of lockdown
so that that's not why we're going for
that
that approach uh we do think that the
local measures uh are right
and i repeat my gratitude to uh local
leadership
uh across the country uh people who've
uh who are helping to get the are down
get the virus done uh
in their uh neighborhoods in their uh
amongst their electorates and and as
we've seen plenty
of of great local leadership and and
that's what we're going to
uh continue with we're going to continue
to to work with people across the
country but it depends on all of us the
it's it's down to all of us ready to uh
to to follow the guidance
uh hands face space do the we haven't
said that yet this press conference so
hands face space uh do the uh essential
stuff
that you know uh makes sense uh
take a test if you have symptoms
self-isolate if you're
uh contacted by uh by nhs test and trace
uh that's the way uh we can do it uh
together
we can get the r down keep
kids in school keep our schools open and
keep
our economy moving and bounce back more
strongly and the package
that we've outlined today is about doing
just that
keeping our economy moving keeping jobs
supporting
jobs and livelihoods throughout the
pandemic thank you all very much thank
you